Finding Aid for Bethel A.M.E. Church (Detroit, Mich.) records, 1897-1990s
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bethel A.M.E. Church (Detroit, Mich.) records 1897-1990s1912-1969
Bethel A.M.E. Church (Detroit, Mich.)
2 microfilm rolls; 0.2 linear ft. and 3 oversize items
Quarterly conference reports; record books with lists of members, baptisms, marriages, and related information; minute books of trustees and various church groups; scattered historical and background information and photographs.
mf332c; mf333c; 0072; Ba 2; UBAm; UBAl
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The church (donor no. 8922 ) allowed the library to make copies (microfilm and photographic) of its records in December 2000. Duplicates of some items were given to the library.
The record group is open for research.
In 1839 a group of 50 black citizens of Detroit formed together as the Colored Methodist Society. After a period of growth and discussion, the members of the Society decided to associate themselves with African Methodism. On May 10, 1841, the congregation organized itself as Bethel African Methodist Church. Some years later, on July 30, 1849, the church was formally incorporated.
The Society moved several times in this early period. When first established, members met in Old Military Hall which the Detroit Common Council had, at first loaned, but shortly thereafter, donated to the Society for its meetings. This structure soon proved inadequate and thus under the leadership of Rev. Edward Heart, Bethel built its first church, a brick structure located on the southside of Lafayette Street, just behind the Old Military Hall. This church building, built at a cost of $2,000, was dedicated September 19,1847. Another church building followed in the late 1880s. At that time, the Rev. James Henderson led the congregation in raising money for a second Bethel Church, to be located on the corner of Napoleon and Hastings Streets. The cornerstone for this church, built at a cost of $21,000 ($3,000 for the lot and $18,000 for the construction), was laid December 22,1889. Under the leadership of Reverend Joseph Gomez (1919-1927), Bethel built its third church building. Reverend Gomez purchased the lots and an adjoining two-family brick house at Frederick and St. Antoine. This church was completed and dedicated June 7,1925. This edifice remained the home of Bethel until 1974 when, under the ministry of the Reverend Maurice J. Higginbothan, the church relocated to a more visible site in the community on three and one-half acres on Warren Boulevard, bounded by St. Antoine Street on the West and 1-75 Service Drive on the East. This new structure was completed at a cost of $1,500,000.00 and dedicated December 1974.
Missions and service to the community have long been important to Bethel. As examples, on November 2,1871, Reverend G. C. Booth, pastor of Bethel, along with thirteen members of the Church organized a Mission and Sunday School and named it Ebenezer out of which the still thriving Ebenezer A.M.E. Church was begun. On September 20,1877, Rev. James Henderson organized the "Self Denial Club" later to be named "The Ladies Helping Hand Society." And under the pastorate of Reverend J. P. Q. Wallace, a social service department was established, October 11, 1911, which developed into an agency for helping people, newly emigrated to Michigan, find jobs and housing.
Reverend William H. Peck began his leadership of Bethel on June 17,1928. Under his guidance the debt of the new church was liquidated. Also importantly, Reverend Peck conceived the idea of the Booker T. Washington Trade Association, while Mrs. Peck was instrumental in founding the equally important Detroit Housewives' League. These organizations were formed primarily to assist struggling black businesses during the depression. The Pecks nurtured these and other organizations into vehicles for improving the economic condition of church members and friends. The Fannie B. Peck Credit Union, conceived and organized by Mrs. Peck, was the first black credit union in America to become state chartered.
Further information about the church, including a listing of its pastors, will be found within the records, especially the anniversary brochures published by the church.
The microfilmed records of Bethel A.M.E. Church of Detroit, Michigan include church record books and reports, minute books of church governing bodies and organizations, and a scattering of issues of the church newsletter, The Bethel Booster. The original materials include published historical and other background information about the church. There is also a scattering of published church materials, such as bulletins, newsletters, and a membership directory. Finally, the church allowed the library to copy selected photographs of church activities, groups, and personalities.
Subjects:
Bethel A.M.E. Church (Detroit, Mich.); African Methodist Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; African American churches--Michigan--Detroit.; African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Peck, William H.; Roberts, Joseph L., 1897-1977.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Detroit.; Bethel A.M.E. Church (Detroit, Mich.); Afro-Americans--Michigan--Michigan--Detroit.; Churches--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Detroit (Mich.)--Churches.; Gomez, Joseph, 1890-1979.; Roberts, Joseph L., 1897-1977.; Osborne, Norman V.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Church record books and reports
  - Record book containing lists of pastors, members, communicants, baptisms, marriages, funerals, etc., 1912-1919 (Reel 1)
    (includes extensive history of the church)
  - Record book containing lists of pastors, members, communicants, baptisms, marriages, funerals, etc., 1919-1938 (Reel 1)
  - Record book containing lists of pastors, members, communicants, baptisms, marriages, funerals, etc., 1942-1969 (Reel 1)
    (membership listed in separate volume)
  - Register of church membership, 1942-1968 (Reel 1)
  - Quarterly Conference reports, 1897-1919 (Reel 1)
- Minute books
  - Trustees minute book, 1911-1920 (Reel 2)
  - Steward and Trustees minutes book, 1915-1925 (Reel 2)
  - Silent Workers of Bethel A.M.E. Church minute book, 1921-1922 (Reel 2)
  - Bethel Gleaners Club minute book, 1950-1953 (Reel 2)
  - Bethel Gleaners Club minute book, 1953-1956 (Reel 2)
  - Bethel Gleaners Club minute book, 1956-1961 (Reel 2)
  - Sunday School minute book, 1919-1921 (Box 2)
  - Minute book (multiple uses); contains
    - Board minutes, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Annual Church Planning Conference, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Building Committee meetings, 1968-1972 (Box 2)
    - Church Conference minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Trustees minutes, 1975 (Reel 2)
- Publications
  - Bethel Booster, 1955-1961 (scattered issues) (Reel 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Historical and background information, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Church anniversary programs (Box 1)
  - Church directory (Box 1)
  - Church bulletins (Box 1)
  - Church newsletters (Box 1)
  - Programs, etc (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Photographs
  Photographs (mainly copyprints) include portraits of pastors Joseph Gomez, Joseph L. Roberts, and Norman V. Osborne; also photos of church building and of church services and groups.
  (also in oversize folders UBAm and UBAl)
  - Church building (Box 1)
  - Church groups and meetings (Box 1)
  - Church pastors and other individuals (Box 1)
  - Church services (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of photographs not copied (Box 1)